[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer or
/ software welcome listeners to a new
episode of software engineering radio
today it's my great pleasure to have
David Hannum on Hanson I hope I
pronounced that right on the show I'm
David is well known to the community is
the creator of Ruby on Rails he's also a
partner at a company called Basecamp
which was formerly called 37signals
which is also very well known and today
we're going to talk about obviously Ruby
on Rails a bit at least but not only
we'll try to get some of your opinions
and other things out to the world as
well so let's jump right in welcome to
the show David thank you very much
happening so um I'll basically assume
that everybody in the world knows Ruby
on Rails but maybe I'm wrong so why
don't you give us the up-to-date
one-paragraph
introduction to what rails actually is
and what the current state of it is sure
Ruby on Rails is a full stack web
development framework which basically
means that it includes just about
everything you need to make great
applications like github or Basecamp or
Airbnb or any of the other many
applications that's been made over the
years with Ruby and rails we're at just
about to release version 5 the framework
is about 12 13 years old I got started
in 2003 as an extraction from Basecamp
and I've been working on it ever since
I think that's there's a lot more
interesting facts about about Ruben
Reyes really it was extracted from a
from a working application as opposed to
having been created and then looking for
something that you can build with it
right absolutely I think that's why it
has resonated so well because it's not
sort of just invention out of thin air
is extraction out from real problems
that I was facing trying to use
to build a web application and we have
carried this ethos forward ever since
that Rails is not backed by a large
group of consultants who just travel
around from shop to shop to sort of help
with problems perhaps and then try to
extract generic patterns of that the
majority of people work on Ruby on Rails
are working on Ruby on Rails from the
vantage point of a specific application
that they're working on so someone might
be working github in their extracting
the problems that they hid their
engineering solutions we can put it into
into rails and of course I continue to
work on Basecamp so whenever I face new
challenges as has been the case with the
most recent version of Basecamp version
3 where we leveled up on real time and
went deep with WebSockets Presto that's
a new framework for rails action cable
and that ships as part of rails 5 and I
think the reason that's important is
when you're trying to solve other
people's problems it's very very easy to
go wrong to imagine that they have
certain problems in a certain way and
then that's simply not so when you're
dealing with your own problems well at
the very least you know you're solving
your own problems so at the very least
you're making a solution that's good for
an audience of one which is infinitely
better than making something that's
created in a vacuum of that audience of
a vacuum of direct experience and then
of course what has turned out is that
when I extract problems I hit from
hidden base camp
well I'm not a beautiful unique
snowflake most people most of the time
are hitting the same problems I'm
hitting when I'm creating the web
application I think one of the one of
the interesting things about rails also
is that it has had a strong influence
than many other frameworks so a lot of
things that were that started out in
rails at least in my experience were
seen appear in other frameworks as well
do you think or what what do you think
is unique about rails what makes it
different from all the others sure yeah
as you say there's lots of the idea
that we've been holding over the years
that's taken root and other frameworks
which is awesome when I got started with
Ruby on Rails it was common that people
would spend many many hours or even days
just setting up the skeleton of their
application this was certainly true in
the Java world where you basically
needed to do two days of XML situps
before you even just have the skeleton
going to say hello world and even so in
in PHP or other more immediate
frameworks there was a lot of just
initial exercise well rails Timmons it
like did that's silk when you start a
new application you should be able to
run two commands and configure one
database and and off to the races then
you're off to actually implement
application logic not plumbing so that
was one of those early advances I think
we got from rails that there really took
hold but many of the other ideas from
rails that are less about just a single
technique and more about the philosophy
behind it have not been cloned which i
think is why rails continues to be so
controversial in fact for a lot of
people the pillars of of the rails
doctrine as I recently wrote up includes
a number of the world Safa chol points
where programmers to this day continue
to disagree I think the primary one that
we've hold and held dear in Ruby on
Rails communities is this notion of
focusing on programmer happiness it's
not enough for application to merely
work it's not enough for to be fast it's
not enough to do all the other technical
objective parameters that we've been
measuring software on for a long time
they also have to make the creator's
happy because this has all sorts of
wonderful spillover effects most
importantly automotive Asian and
motivated programmers are simply more
proactive programmers and having
productive programmers is one of the key
challenges I'd say of the whole software
movement
that fighting back and pushing back
against needing ever bigger teams
requires an increasing ever-increasing
amount of productivity from a single
programmer so we need to constantly make
the frameworks and the libraries in the
Ruby on Rails world better and more
productive in order to counteract the
spiraling ambitions that people have for
an application is supposed to do all
these things nowadays well I believe
that the cornerstone of that is to
ensure that a programmer consists in
front of a computer for eight hours a
day even if there's not eight hours of
pure productivity but be happy most of
the time and that happiness is
influenced strongly by tools that if she
chooses to use and Ruby on Rails has
focused on what for a lot of people is
considered silly things aesthetics is
one thing how the code looks and coming
up with subtle nuanced variations of
methods in order to just make the code
prettier just make the code clearer or
shorter or more concise for me one of
the early revelations of this was the
keyword unless so when I first hit Ruby
that was one of those things where I
just went wow that blows my mind like
unless is the same as if not it's just a
more concise and in many ways a prettier
way of saying the same thing so is the
fact that you can place unless either
before the statement or after the
statement in Ruby so you can have these
subtle shifts in intonation where you
put the pressure in sentence of Ruby
code that is just a joy and utter joy to
work with
and it's this expressiveness that
remains both so dear to many rubyists
hearts and at the same time is
continuously critiqued by other
languages and communities as a clear
counter is the Python motto of
preferably one way and only one way to
do things
ruby has in many ways it's a complete
opposite preferably many ways as many
ways as possible in many of the same
ways that the English language is not
what is it that they got new speak down
to 500 different words no the English
language is in excess of 200,000 words
and that is a lot of its beauty is a lot
of its beauty is expressiveness in in
these sorts of different shades this is
one of the things that I think about in
particularly because I'm a Dane and the
Danish language is only used by 5
million people and perhaps my
consequence it's a relatively small
language compared to English it has
about half the words if you at least
don't count all the put together words
that that you have in Danish so there
are certain things one of the examples I
often use this is the word light or
candle in Danish that's the same word
use there's just one word for both
candle and light that's to me is a
example of not a very expressive
language and that ink is simply a better
language because it has this way of
distinguishing these subtle differences
that they don't rely merely just on
context to derive what the true meaning
is you have more words to do it with so
that's a really long way of saying that
in Ruby and rails we continue to
optimize the programmer happiness to the
point that we're willing to trade off
other things and that I think is where
the rubber really hits the road that
lots of other communities may say that a
lot well we're also about programmer
happiness but they're not willing to
give up other valuable things to have it
they're not willing for example to give
up performance or they're not willing to
give up type safety or other sort of
impediments to programmer happiness in
terms of
being drags and program of productivity
so in Ruby on Rails which is saying
we're willing to trade those things I
will make this program go slower
such that when I look at the code I am
happier that remains a deeply
controversial statement that I think
lots of programmers would not sign up to
so that's just one example we have many
several of these examples of major
philosophical planks into Ruby on Rails
community that was part of the
foundation why I made the framework at
the same place because they were in the
first place because I had these ideas
that were different from the ideas that
were being expressed at the time and
continued to be expressed in other
environments and at the same time they
remain controversial such that rails and
Ruby remains unique because most people
are not only even though they might be
capable of of cloning and following
these things would you simply disagree
so we end up in different paths which is
wonderful I think that is one of the
beauties of programming especially
programming for the web is that we can
disagree and we can have this diversity
of implementation if diversity of
language that we don't all have to speak
the one language that is the travesty
that's reserved for developing on native
platforms so let me try to face you with
with a few of the criticisms that I
typically hear when people talk about
Ruby on Rails and interestingly enough
when preparing this podcast that's a
very very controversial input from my
co-hosts who wanted me to ask you a lot
of things so let me address just some of
them one one is one that you already
mentioned which is the speed and
performance and maybe related to the
scalability of the whole of the whole
thing so in your opinion I'll be
obviously it's worth it but is it maybe
only worth sacrificing those things if
you're not building serious things don't
you as soon as you build something that
you really want to make money with or
turn into a sustainable business don't
you just have to switch to something
different and give up a little of the
happiness and aesthetics and the other
qualities insurance is having something
that's more efficient and faster and
scales better I'll give you the summary
first
no longer twelve or thirteen years ago
when I started working with Ruby do you
think ruby was faster slower than it is
today do you think computing power was
more expensive or less expensive than it
is today
and do you think that programmer talent
was more or less expensive than it is
today
well ruby was much much slower twelve
years ago
computing power was significantly more
expensive and programmers were much
cheaper even under those parameters
basecamp the app that I developed with
Ruby on Rails has been tremendously
profitable and successful even though it
served
millions and millions of customers and
even though it's built on Ruby on Rails
so a base camp could be a success twelve
years ago given those differences in the
environment think about how much better
things are today think about how many
more environments were the cost of Ruby
on Rails and in terms of slower
computing is just dramatically offset by
the happiness and productivity that
flows into the programmers and the fact
that you need fewer of them the fact
that the ones that you have are so much
happier the fact that you simply get
more stuff done quicker now that is not
to say that they're doing that there are
domains where Ruby simply isn't fast
enough there absolutely is at certain
points for example if you're trying to
process I know how many tweets that they
do a second right now let's say they do
100,000 tweets a second at peak I don't
know that could be off by a factor of 10
but if you're processing simply incoming
pieces of 140 characters and you have a
need a pipeline for handling that and
shoving that into a database like yes at
that point
Ruby might very well not be the best
choice there because you're simply at a
scale
where the economics do start to kind of
matter although what's funny is if you
look at the balance sheet or quarterly
reports from from even a Twitter what do
you think that they're spent the most of
the money on you think they're spending
the most of the money on hardware what
do you think they're spending the most
of their money on San Francisco
programmer salaries I'll spoil the
surprise here and say it's the latter
but even in that case the whole purpose
of exploratory software which Twitter
certainly falls under is that first you
have to figure out what it is that you
want to build and while you're figuring
out what it is that you want to build
and how you want to build it doing so in
clay it's a lot easier than doing so in
iron iron is a very inflexible material
that has to be treated in all sorts of
interesting ways with dangerous
materials and techniques to bend it clay
you just bend it with your hands Ruby is
like clay many other languages that have
higher performance are more like iron
and that is not to say that at some
point this sort of you want to replace
the clay once you figured out what it is
that you actually want to make and what
you want to build with an iron structure
what I do find interesting though is
that it is vastly vastly hilariously
overrated how often that conversion
needs to happen there's basically just a
small handful in my opinion of
businesses that truly need to make that
conversion the number of massive
businesses from Shopify to Airbnb to
github to Basecamp
to whatever else have you that continue
to work and thrive by building their
applications in clay it's just
overwhelming overwhelming to the point
that the argument at this point is
ridiculous in fact and that even posting
the question comes off as slightly
ignorant it was much easier to post this
question in 2004 when we didn't have
this legion of examples of
billion-dollar businesses even though
that's not
in my book alone qualification of
success but to the people who ask
questions like this I think that that is
the kind of arguments that they they
need to hear back that you can ask these
questions to 2004 and and legitimately
say okay let's have a discussion about
that asking that question in 2016 is
simply just ignorant and is ignorant in
the face of overwhelming evidence to the
contrary
so yes Ruby remains low in performance
in many of the same ways that you could
say I don't know the sick Java is low in
performance to assemble right now you
could write web applications in
assembler it is technically possible to
do that it would be incredibly stupid
because the benefits you get back simply
are not worth it so when you look at
something like performance for example
you get to a point where things are
simply good enough for most web
applications if you can just get your
server-side response time down to around
let's say 100 milliseconds or
thereabouts as an average you are far
far far into the land of good enough
that the responsiveness of your
application is no longer governed by how
quickly your server-side can respond
it's governed by all the other factors
of how the internet works and how HTTP
works and how caching works and the way
you use acids and with videos web fonts
and how much JavaScript you have and bla
bla bla bla bla bla that if you look at
the size of a whole request the server
side part of that becomes a tiny little
vanishing part so the benefit of moving
from let's say a 1 second server side
response time to say let's just say 300
milliseconds server side response time
that is significant there is benefit
there absolutely and we should try to do
get to that point now once you hit that
point the benefit of moving from 300
milliseconds to 30 milliseconds is a lot
less orders of magnitude less it's kind
of like the same parallel I I make when
I talk about business and success the
difference in someone's life between
having zero dollars and
$1,000,000 phenomenon very very large
difference right like it does all sorts
of good things to sort of your daily
life the difference between having 1
million dollars and having two million
dollars vanishingly small many many many
orders of magnitude less even though
it's the same absolute improvement 1
million dollars one way 1 million
dollars the other way right the same is
true for performance once you get to a
state of good enough and for web
applications I generally say below 300
milliseconds and if you can hit a
hundred milliseconds which is where we
are for a lot of requests for Basecamp 3
well you're in the golden land spending
valuable precious programming time to
suffer in iron core environments just to
make that a little better is such an
utter waste of time
and that is where the true broken
economic success well you could argue
that it's not only performance but also
the amount of resources that you need to
get a certain throughput that is very
different if you if you if you can get
by with a tenth of the of the hardware
then you do save money admittedly you're
absolutely right that it's not only
that's that's not maybe not may not be
the the major point in your cost
structure is developer time it'd be way
more expensive and very often is but
still there is a difference in having to
use I don't know 10 servers versus 100
service isn't there there is and I think
that some scales for some companies as
the example we just talked about like
processing the hundred thousand incoming
tweets the economics can flip where it
is worth making things in iron right but
for the 99.9% it's simply not so that
for the 99% every single time you can
trade a more inefficient programming
language to get more productivity back
it's worth it programming salaries are
only going one way up computing costs
only going one way down so if you want
to be on the right side of trends in
history then that's where you gotta
place your bets and this is where it's
sometimes hard
people have been in the industry for a
long time to recognize that the sands
have shifted in 1995 this was not true
you could not just use ruby in the same
ways that you're using ruby today it
would simply be too expensive the ratio
between cost of servers versus costs of
programmers was completely different in
1995 right but now we're 20 years later
and it's very different the problem is
that the people who were around in 1995
those economics are imprinted on their
retina they're imprinted in their skull
in many of the same ways that if any of
you grandparents that live through major
Kannamma crises either Second World War
or depressions or so on sometimes it's
the sillies things that are just
imprinted into their skull like for my
grandparents it was this notion that if
you wanted to have a really luxurious
breakfast you would just layer on the
butter because you couldn't get butter
in 1944 in Denmark right so butter
became this symbol of luxury this symbol
of now we're really doing well so now
let's let's really have a feast and
let's layer up these croissants which is
so much butter that you're gonna gag
right they didn't realize that the
economic model had changed that butter
simply wasn't a precious resource in
1986 when I was forced to eat fully
buttered up croissant night and I think
the exact same thing is true for
programmers who have lived through the
depression of computing resources as as
early ages were and it's just incredibly
hard to break out of that like those
habits just lay deep in our operating
system as humans and rewriting that code
not a small task let me just ask one
final question regarding rails because I
do want to talk about other topics as
well this is actually a criticism that I
hear from from people who do use rails
not from those who've never used it or
never used in earnest which is that it
has become more and more complicated
over the years that has accumulated more
and more things that are included in the
batteries included concept so it has
become a lot more complex
then it wasn't the beginning it has
become way harder to understand so that
many people who use it understand but a
fraction of it and they don't really
know what they're doing with this with
this very powerful thing do you see that
as a as a problem or do you think that's
and that's an unjustified and
substantiated criticism I think it's a
feeling but let me unpack the feeling
because I think the feeling has root in
some factors that are actually not that
correlated so first yes rails is much
much larger now than it was 10 years ago
but if you look at trying to do the same
thing let's say creating a simple
controller that iterates over a table
view of items in a in a database when
you look at a single use case like that
that's my measure of success is rails
more complicated at solving that use
case than it was 10 years ago the answer
is absolutely not far less code is
needed the code that is needed is far
clearer the help us that we have to do
it are just much better so if you
compare use case to use case I think
rails has jumped leaps and bounds now
the difference is that the number of use
cases rails was willing to able to solve
in 2005 it's far smaller than the number
of use cases it's willing to solve in
2016 in 2005 if you wanted to protect
yourself against let's say cross-site
scripting attacks or anything like that
well you're on your own you research
that problem from scratch you learn
everything there is to learn about it
and then you build your own solution now
rails in that sense is simple it simply
doesn't solve the problem like that's
very simple right like if you just say
hey you have 20 problems you need to
solve making your web application we are
the simple framework we solve 2 of those
good luck with the other 18 like that is
a simple framework and there are many
frameworks that's come since rails that
take that approach and that is the
problem with the word simplicity it's
such a devious term
because people empowered with this
notion of goodness when in my book if I
have to solve 20 problems and my toolbox
only gives me assistance in solving two
of them
that's not simpler my final application
is far more complex because I had to
research and figure out all the 18 other
problems that I needed to solve in depth
now
rails today let's say rails 2005 sold
five of you twenty problems rails today
solves eighteen of your twenty problems
that means that we have let me do the
math here thirteen other elements of
rails that now need to be built and you
could say understood if you want to
understand the whole thing but that's
where I go like why do you need to
understand the whole thing most of the
time the purpose of building things into
a framework or toolbox is to alleviate
the programmer from having to understand
problems from first principle because if
you have to understand every single
problem of a modern web application from
first principle before you can do
anything well off to school for you for
the next six years right like no one is
willing to do that no one is going to
make that trade we all rely on the
giants that went before us and we all
built on on the things that we have and
we're better off before it but yes it
does mean that there are more things to
solve 18 out of 20 use cases you simply
need more tools in your box but the
individual tools need not be any more
complex in fact they might they very
well be a lot better and I content that
they most certainly are if you look at
the recent major expansions in in scope
and breadth of the rails framework they
come from let's take just the two most
recent frameworks active job which
provides you with an abstraction and an
AC setup for using asynchronous job
servers and running logic gates in
chrome you see right the reason why I
know that's so much better than what
went before it is because obviously I
did jobs before we had active job the
amount of code I was able to rip out of
base camp when we plugged in
to job substantial the amount of
complexity and setup and decisions about
Oh should I pick this thing should I put
the other thing that we alleviated by
billing it into the framework awesome
the most recent example actually capable
is is anyone actually tried to do
WebSockets from scratch from first
principle let's try to understand the
specs that are involved and then try to
do it where you could say HTML and HTTP
1:1 and and so forth you can get sort of
like you can understand those things
easily from first principles in in not
very long time understanding WebSockets
from first principles and digging
through all the underlying specs and
incompatibilities and so forth major
task which is why most people just did
not use it right so again there you have
simplicity well if I just don't choose
to take advantage of the real time web
through WebSockets my application is
simpler my framework can be simpler
that's not the notion that we're
interested in with Ruby on Rails I am
Not Afraid of expanding the scope and
solving more out of the twenty use cases
that most people need to solve for most
applications most of the time and that
was always the governing principle for
Ruby on Rails was hey let's share all
the solutions that we that most of us
run into most of the time and as the web
has become more complicated in some
senses there are more of those solutions
and the fact that rails facilitates the
sharing of those is exactly why we're
still where we are today that that is
incredibly valuable but it's also again
one of those controversial things it
goes counter to a lot of near and dear
health beliefs about how software should
be made by most programmers which is
subscribing to things like the UNIX
philosophy
oh well don't make frameworks just make
small pointed tools and then to use it
and figure out how to put that together
themselves rails wind in the opposite
direction said no we're going to make an
integrated system where all the parts
are designed not to be used alone in
isolation but in fact to be used
together in combination and that
designing tools with the knowledge of
the other tools that's going to be used
with enables us to go on a much higher
level of integration and smoothness of
the use and and all these are the
benefits that we get from it but as I
said still deeply controversial aspect
and even within people who do otherwise
like Ruby on Rails this pull towards the
in my opinion shallow definition of
simplicity is simply or less stuff
solving less use cases remains a
powerful one and it's not until you
unpack that emotion because I can have
that emotion in time to where I look at
the rescue of a thinker like wow that's
a lot of things and then it usually
rifle through the things and see like
hey can I find some stuff here that I
could kick out and sometimes we can we
do occasionally take things out that
they at one point were part of problems
that most people need to solve most the
time they no longer are
so we kick them out like XML processing
used to be a much bigger deal no it's
not so where else does less to
accommodate that and does more to
accommodate let's say Jason processing
right so things do evolve over time but
yeah it's a long wait I will not make
any excuses for solving more of the
twenty use cases that most people need
to do most of time mm-hm
okay this episode of se radio is
sponsored by indeed prime indeed prime
helps software developers simplify their
job search and land their dream job
candidates get immediate exposure to the
best tech companies with just one simple
application to indeed profit companies
on primes exclusive platform message
candidates with salary and equity
upfront
the average software developer gets five
employer contacts and an average salary
offer of one hundred and twenty five
thousand dollars indeed prom is a
hundred percent free for candidates no
strings attached and when you're hired
indeed prime gives you a five thousand
dollar bonus to say thanks for using
prime and two thousand dollars when you
refer a friend who gets hired go sign up
at indeed.com / se radio
um you mentioned that you that you add
stuff to rails and that you embrace
modern things in some some aspects you
remain quite conservative some people
were to say one one of those examples is
that rails is still very much focused on
on a classical server-side HTML
rendering model as opposed to how many
people these days believe they need to
build applications I'm showing my bias
here probably shouldn't be doing that
but many people believe that these days
the server side should be simpler and
there should be more more logic in the
client which is what a lot of single
page application frameworks built in
JavaScript are appearing and some people
use rails I'm aware of that to just
build a server-side API but I don't but
I believe that's not something you
follow as a as a or you would recommend
something people do can you elaborate a
bit on your view on that sure so first
of all I say one of the features we're
putting in rails 5 is actually an API
mode where the rails stack gets paired
down just for the purpose of
implementing a domain model and using
all the wonderful tools we have from
active record an active job and all the
other backing to build a great domain
model but then exposing that domain
month purely through Jason replies right
so we're accommodating that approach in
rails 5 and I think that's one of those
areas where I've come to realize that
rails today is such a big tent that we
can very well accommodate and
collaborate with people who have
distinctly different ideas of how the
final application should be built in
most cases and benefit from it so if you
want to use ember react or whatever else
have you by the time this podcast comes
out there's probably four new JavaScript
frameworks that you had to learn in the
interim and if you want to use any of
them with rails rails will welcome you
with open arms and it will be an awesome
experience for building your domain
model because I think one of the
fallacies that often go into this is
that oh well if I'm building most of my
user interface on the client side well
then I don't need something like rails
and I golike really do
if you look at the rails set of use
cases that it solve how many of those
use cases are related to HTML very
little bit very little code in rails is
focused around HTML we have helpers and
we're back to view and we do have some
stuff around it but the vast vast
majority are abroad all the other
elements of connecting things to the
Internet and building up at the main
model and so forth so all the benefit of
that is still present whether you choose
to build your HTML on the server side or
you choose to do it in the client side
now all that being said I think this
current trend and chase of the single
page application built through
client-side embassy for a lot of
applications a lot of the time is a
blind alley and I think it's a blind
alley in the same way that this industry
has changed other blind alleys in the
past everything from flash to
Silverlight to Java to whatever I
understand that these things are
different and I also appreciate and
sympathize far more with people who want
to use the native constructs of the web
of JavaScript and HTML and so on in the
browser from those early attempts but I
considered still to be reminiscent and
some of that remin incidence comes from
the arguments that are being used to
justify the client-side embassy sort of
move and a lot of those are things like
sophisticated modern ambitious these
labels that we apply to the UI and the
user experience and then we infer that
those things are good in fact a lot of
the times when I encounter UIs that can
be described as sophisticated I go like
this is a piece of crap like things just
don't work properly or it's just it's
too ornate and too complicated for its
own good and that so much of the
information systems that we built today
are far better off when we're
constricted and restricted from using
all this so-called sophistication it
reminds me of again the same arguments
that we used for flash where you'd go
like well flash don't have these native
elements that
CML has four four form inputs or
whatever but look at all this other
stuff we could do you could make your
own but you are not constrained in any
way from these shackles of HTML and I go
like I want the shackles put on the
handcuff please
HTML and the restricted expressive never
that is its greatest benefit is its
greatest gift to the use of interfaces
of the world constricting people from
being able to just dream in Photoshop
now again client Embassy's not all that
I'm just saying that there's a
similarity between the arguments used in
the two camps that I find both striking
and disconcerning in any case my
argument is merely that most of the time
you do not need the sophistication and
giving up this sophistication means
gaining something else productivity that
building these elaborate clients at
embassy structures is complicated work I
don't think even most of the most ardent
proponents in that camp would would
question that getting this stuff set up
is complicated
I was believe they would say it's more
productive I don't agree with them but I
believe that it's a common feeling that
it's more productive if you have
something like let's say angular it's
easier to build something that is as you
say fancy and sophisticated if you do it
on the client side then if you have to
do the Meserve aside you know obviously
don't agree with that right yeah yes if
you take us a given that the user
interface has to be this quote/unquote
sophisticated monstrosity yes perhaps
you could make the argument that this
infant built a monstrosity this way but
you can also just say hey let's not
build a monstrosity and if you
reconfigure the problem definition that
the monstrosity is not an assumption is
not a given well then I think the
productivity argument quickly deflates
and come back to earth so as in hey can
we solve this underlying problem in a
far simpler way where we do not need
such a fancy sophisticated user
interface for it and if that's the scope
of your problem definition well then it
becomes a lot far simpler I don't think
that there are even I don't think there
are any people in the
clients at embassy camp who will look at
a very plain webpage that maybe has a
form that could be submitted or whatever
and say like oh that would be much
simpler if we added 15 layers of
JavaScript gunk on top of it so at some
root level I think there isn't this
there is an agreement that the
client-side embassy complicates matters
but you could say the disagreement is
whether that's worth it or not whether
we want the same things and many cases
that just say we don't want the same
things I don't like the user interfaces
we're building it's a Basecamp far
better suited in the majority of cases
from not being sophisticated that I
usually look at the things that we do
build that are sophisticated and then
say I wish we hadn't gone so
sophisticated now again this is always a
matter of specifics if you look at some
of the things we've done at Basecamp for
example we recently spent a whole year
building a client-side MVC model for a
brand new text editor called Trix
and in that case absolutely that's the
right thing to do like you have to build
a very complicated sophisticated model
on the client side to solve that problem
because the fidelity you need to have
responsiveness at the keypress is very
different different than the
responsiveness you need at the click a
link press write like if you're typing
things and your text enter can't keep up
with you well it's not gonna be a text
editor most people gonna be happy to use
but if you're clicking a link and that
link takes let's say 150 milliseconds to
render well things are fine so you have
to look at the individual problems to
try to solve and partition things
accordingly and what I'm saying is that
most applications most of the time when
it comes to information systems the vast
majority of that application does not
need sophistication and complexity of
the clients at embassy reserve that from
when you truly need it which is in fact
much the same argument we're making on
native so we have native apps for four
different platforms and if you just take
the native mobile apps for example
take the iOS app the iOS app is probably
90% maybe even 95% web-based it's
running on turbo lanes 5 and then we
have 5% where the attractive interaction
speed and the fidelity really does
matter to the point where when we level
up to native that's a big win and then
we take that win and you're saying like
Oh for this 5% of the application let's
do native which again for us back to the
earliest discussion we had like oh well
Ruby's not fast enough well if you
actually do hit cases where ruby is not
fast enough it's usually again the 5%
are more likely than 1% just take that
1% of rewriting something faster reap
the benefits of productivity from the
other 99 percent of the other 95 percent
that's a completely valid way of going
forward the previous version based game
that we had had a very sophisticated
client-side MVC driven calendar system
where again you had the same thing there
was a very high level of fidelity needed
to make this feel good hey we just took
that one part of the application and
made the client side embassy and then we
continued on with the productivity gains
of the rest of the application and not
using those techniques and using far
simpler techniques so in danger we have
this saying of don't shoot
sparrows with cannons I don't know if
that's almost an English saying suppose
available in German at least oh it is ok
I love that same because yes you could
absolutely shoot a sparrow with a cannon
it's just not a good use of cannons time
and it's overkill for the sparrow right
there are simpler ways of getting the
solution that you want which is no
sparrows on your front porch right you
don't have to bring out a cannon - to
deal with that problem in fact it's more
likely to just put holes everywhere that
is the analogy I will choose to go with
for this ok you briefly mentioned
turbolinks and I think that's a plays an
important role in why you were able to
stick with a with a server-side HTML
model for much of your mobile
applications can you do it too little
technical detail on that
we started working on the second version
of base camp which was I think about
2012 plant site development Zorn was
already taking off and people were
enamored by the benefits of not having
to reload your whole thing between each
paint requests and the benefits of that
game in terms of rendering time their
responsiveness and so on right that was
I mean
Ajax even came before that but then got
truly on steroids by the time we said
hey what does the whole thing was just a
guess now I looked at all that and went
hmm I wonder if there's a way where we
can get the vast majority of the benefit
this feeling or responsiveness without
giving up the simplicity of the request
response model without giving up the
simplicity of simply just generating the
entire HTML document on the server side
because there's such great value in that
so I started exploring ways and pcaps
with an early approach to sort of doing
something like this they this is
something pioneered at github and they
went down a little bit different path
where they were trying to just pick out
some partials that they went oh if we
just had to replace this one part of the
page it'd be faster
I think the triple-n's realization was
like hey that's actually not the problem
generating the whole HTML document
server-side is not where the speed
benefit is going to be hidden especially
not if you're using judicial use of
caching through Russian dolls strategies
and so forth but turbolinks
gave us this notion that we could turn
what was essentially a CGI model where
every click would throw away the entire
client-side UI and require it to be
compiled again afresh and go to a
persistent process model which if your
listeners are old enough to remember
this is also something we went through
on the server side in the old days CT I
had this model it would spin up an
entire process compile the code usually
at the Perl process the one request and
throw out the whole damn process away
then do the next thing again the next
time which that works fine if you have a
very small core of things you want to
say if you just want to say hello world
are put in the current time or something
that's fine you can throw them away the
whole process well the more
sophisticated you get the more the
larger your structure get the larger
your process is skin well the worse that
works like it didn't take that long for
us to figure out that hey maybe we
shouldn't be throwing away the entire
process between every request what if we
just reuse the process well then we
don't have to compile the whole system
again and all these other benefits from
it why is that a controversial notion on
the client-side because that's basically
the model that we've just taken straight
over well I think the controversial
point comes in in that people wanted
both ways or either way you'd say either
they want to do or a distinct they want
to do full-on single page app with a
heavy client-side MVC framework and then
they sort of accept that okay they have
to write everything in that way what
they want the jQuery supe where they can
just put in any take for a plug-in and
everything would just work on a matigan
well the jQuery soup was designed for
for a plate of CGI for a plate of
disposable processes and with terpil
links we're saying well we want the
persistent processes we want a
persistent JavaScript and CSS
engine running between requests and
there's a large performance benefit from
that it does mean we have to make some
concessions and how we might write the
rest of the JavaScript we want to power
our pages and I think that was what trip
people up at least in the beginning I
see more and more people coming around
to it and I think the benefits of the
turbolinks model the notion that you can
retain full HTML generation on the
client side you can retain the full
request response model has such a appeal
and grounds of simplicity when you
combine it with things like the native
apps that you otherwise would have to
build that I think this is this is going
to get more interest and less knee-jerk
reactions once people realize hey wait a
minute if I have to build a modern app
today do I have to build both a web
application API something on the
client-side one native application from
scratch 100% from on the Android one
native application 1% on iPhone oh what
I do about the Mac
what I do about the windows and all the
sudden I need 50 people just to make an
MVP the productivity benefits are simply
enormous and the fidelity that you give
up in most cases most of the time is
neck double and it's not something that
users cherish if you look at the scores
we have just for the Basecamp apps that
are built on triple links five with this
model I think we have 4.5 rating and a 4
rating or something like that
better ratings that lots and lots of
fully native apps so this is not an
impediment at least in a wide variety of
information systems to giving a great
user experience that basically you're
giving something up something that most
users most the time wouldn't miss ok um
one of the things that has become a
recurring theme we saw that essentially
we have to talk about it now on every se
radio episode is micro services and
micro services and monoliths I know is a
topic that you also have a strong
opinion on as you have the most things
so can you elaborate a bit on your views
on that and tell us how Basecamp is
built yes well I recently posted a full
teresa's on this coming off the last
keynote I gave address Kampf which was
centered around the notion of the
majestic monolith picking the monolithic
pattern with pride and intention not
stumbling into it not accidentally
falling into its pits but putting down
the drawbridge and walking in with your
head held high
that is what base camp is base camp is a
majestic monolith we have explicitly and
intentionally chosen to implement the
vast vast majority of the application
within one large application and then we
have these satellites that
revolve around it and interface with it
as we just talked about even the native
apps or 95% just displaying what the
monoliths sent down the wire and then
they have the five percent of the native
specialization on top of that but I
think it's a it's again it goes back to
the same thing right it goes back to
these notions of simplicity avoiding
over specialization avoiding sort of
patterns that just makes things harder
for you at a time where you do not need
those things micro services and
service-oriented architectures in
general can't be very valid and decent
patterns to follow once you have no
other choice if you have a massive
organization like Amazon it makes total
sense to treat basically one department
as though it was just another place on
your internet from another department
but it has all sorts of costs in
Amazon's case those costs are worth it
because they don't feel like they can
manage having I don't know how many
programmers they have let's say they
have 5,000 programmers working on the
same code base at the same time now
little asterisks a little star on that
is that it's actually interesting is
that both Google and Facebook are big
proponents of the monolithic pattern -
and have these truly humongous repos and
and truly mungus code bases that they
work on I'll put that aside a little bit
because I haven't exploited fully I
don't know whether they've just stumbled
into that but they've chosen it by
design I have a tendency to think that
there are enough smart people built
places that if they've ended up here and
stayed here perhaps it is very well by
design and not just through accident but
let's put that aside for a bit and is
focused on the fact that if you are a
smaller team where it is possible for
every programmer to understand the vast
majority of your application and keep it
in it in their head at the at the same
time well micro services are generally a
terrible idea they're just ways of
making things more complicated and more
convoluted and introducing more
different failure states and failure
modes where things can break down the
difference between making a method call
and making an HTTP call to huge you need
all sorts of provisions around how that
collaboration half
that you simply do not need when you
just make a method call and this goes
back to what I quote the butcher quote
the Martin Fowler law of distributed
computing which I basically paraphrase
as like the first rule of disappear
disability computing is don't distribute
you computing and you don't disturb you
computing until you absolutely
positively have to because not doing so
is so much simpler it is much the same
argument as we just had about
client-side MVC client-side MVC is
basically distributed computing more or
you should say more distributed
computing where client and server take
bigger or where the client takes a
bigger slice of the domain from the
server where what I'm advocating is as
much as we can get away with go for the
monolithic system where you have a
single system that's responsible for
everything the benefits are just
enormous now some of those benefits are
possible because of you because of using
a specific tool separately if you say
well Basecamp 3 is currently twenty five
thousand lines of code if I had to write
that same application and let's say Java
perhaps it'd be two hundred fifty
thousand lines of code well can anyone
keep doing 250 thousand lines of code in
their head at the same time and make
reasonable progress under perhaps not so
perhaps in that case you do have to chop
it off when you're using highly
productive and hide the expressive
environments the time when which you do
have to do that chop off just comes so
much later and it comes to such a larger
scale and that's what I really gets my
goat is when some oh yeah we're a team
of three people and we have like these
four micro services and I just go like
oh Jesus Christ like you have the wrong
role model
get up like your role model is is the
Amazons in the world when you should be
looking at one of the other companies
that have three people doing not doing
that
don't inflict yourself with this extra
pain just because that makes you look
big and that like makes you look
sophisticated but unfortunately like
that's a siren song for programmers
they're more complicated and the more
sophisticated you can then sound talking
about it that's very often correlated to
how smart you think you are let me let
me telling us a little bit for for
Basecamp itself maybe Basecamp is so
simple
that it fits in a monolith I know listen
this is not true but I have to ask you
anyway
sure so how complicated is Basecamp
that's a great question because it's
often product and we've had this
argument since the beginning there well
basically was just a glorified to do
listen yeah perhaps in some ways it is
what's by the way wrong with that but if
you actually look at the fact base game
has over 200 different screens I think
we have 900 or almost a thousand
different controller actions if you get
in those terms perhaps base game is not
so small after all right and I'm just
I've just ran rails stats here we have
205 controllers we have just about 200
models as well no this is not the
biggest system in the world learn tons
of systems that are far bigger but it's
big enough it's big enough step it
drives this organization of 50 people
and millions of workers and tons and
tons of applications are far smaller
than this far smaller application than
base game have been chopped up into
little micro surfaces and been worse off
for it I think one of the things that
you that you mentioned that it seems to
be a recurring theme is this notion of
keeping things simple as simple as they
can possibly be and I believe that
extends to your views on business and
business strategy as well how much of a
similarity do you see between the way
you look at code and the way you look at
the business side of things yeah it's a
great point because I think there are
tons of player panels to draw the reason
I usually don't grab the word simplicity
is as we talked about earlier that you
have can have something that's simple
when it's solving two out of 20 use
cases well I would argue that it's
simpler when you solve 18 out of 20 use
cases so there's a fundamental
disagreement on the word which makes the
word not very helpful because everyone
will use it to describe what they do I
have never talked to a programmer who
said oh I write complicated code right
no one says that
everyone says a lot right simple code
even people writing things in vanilla
Java
I talked to back in the day making k2e
oh this is really simple and just go
like
do not share a common sense of what that
word means obviously right but I will
say that many of the ideas of how to
build the software and how to keep
solving a wide array of use cases with
the least amount of effort at least
amount of a novel effort goes very well
into the business I consider Basecamp as
a business as a system that we should
continue to refactor and hack on and
then we continue to have to deal with
tipping points Basecamp today at close
to 50 people is a different company than
it was at fifteen people and some things
just have tipping points that need to be
addressed in a variety of ways and I
think that's the same thing with with
code there if we had started out signing
Basecamp for how the company should run
when it was 50 people it would not have
been nearly as nice of a company when it
was five people you have to pick
something that's appropriate for your
scale and that's where I reject a lot of
the business advice that's out there is
that it's drawn from these hyper cases
they're drawn from oh okay what's Amazon
doing what's Facebook doing what's
Google doing and just go like that could
not be more irrelevant in many cases to
these small companies that are trying to
learn from the Giants as could be
because oftentimes the patterns that you
need to apply at 10,000 people or a
hundred and eighty percent or 180
degrees the opposite pattern of what you
should apply at 10 people or 15 people
and I think that that lesson of context
which funny enough was part of the
patent language and the way patterns at
least nominally are described in the
technical community is very often lost
I'm guilty of that at times too I
assumed that
the context that I speak of is the
things that I know of so when someone
listens reach something I write they
have to just implicitly say oh well this
is a context that probably applies from
a company between five and fifty people
because that is that what I have
personal experience with right like this
might very well apply different need for
a company of 10,000 what am I also very
well not but at least there's more
grains of salt to be thrown at the
problem so how much do you think people
need to look into the future for doing
that is it a valid strategy strategy to
just solve today's problems and just
don't care about what's gonna happen in
the future and just take the problems
when they arise and specifically talking
about technology and architecture here
how much how much do you have to plan in
advance in your review to make sure that
you can handle for example an explosion
in the number of users that you have and
can you imagine that some people might
use a different approach because they
expect that they will be well maybe not
at the size of Google or Amazon but a
lot bigger yes this is the delusions of
the lottery coupon buyer oh I'm gonna
buy a lottery coupon now so I better get
that mortgage on the huge mansion lined
up and I better get my favorite sports
car picked out and let's see which
Riviera we should go to for the summer
vacation it's a little premature most
people the number one issue that they're
facing is how do we get to the place
where we can be so fortunate as to have
scaling problems it is not to figure out
how can i preempt all these scaling
problems because that doesn't work
anyway
if facebook had sat down oh let's design
the system system works really well from
1.3 billion users do you think that
system would ever have launched no it
wouldn't no one designs systems upfront
that can work for a billion users at
least not of that system does anything
novel or moderately complicated perhaps
it's possible to design a whatsapp for
in advance for a billion users but I
even doubt that the vast vast majority
of scaling stories that we have from all
the survivors who made it to this giant
scale was oh we through the system out
like three times
and they say that and some people look
at that like oh well if I was just
smarter I could not have to do that I
could save these three discs are
discarded system on the way to get there
and I would say like absolutely not like
the whole point of how they got there
how they allowed themselves to get there
was to not worry about what happened
that a billion people because having to
make those considerations up to the
front it's just an utter waste of time
and actually vastly increases the odds
you are not going to make it because
you're spending time on the wrong thing
as we were talking about earlier the
difference between clay and iron before
you figured out what you're trying to
build using iron to build a visit
frustrating experience and not a very
productive one either right first figure
out what it is that you want to build
figure out a way to get as they say like
market fit selling something that people
willing to buy it then once you figure
that out and once you've done to a
billion users worried about how to deal
with that there's virtually no examples
in recorded history the one I keep
hearing about which I'd love to dig into
at one point is is Friendster but almost
no online businesses has ever truly
failed because they did not anticipate
how the system was gonna operate at a
billion users it just doesn't happen and
especially doesn't happen because the
fundamentals that we build on today
shared nothing architecture x' and the
stack approaches that makes sense even
at the low end they can scale incredibly
high basically the architecture using
for base camp
now at at millions of users is very
similar to the architecture that we
started with because the fundamentals
are just sound so it's not like we
needed that much of a different pattern
or strategy to to get there so yes as a
short conclusion do not worry about
tomorrow worry about today today has
plenty of issues for you to deal with
and then worry about tomorrow tomorrow
ok David that was there were those were
perfect last words I think thank you so
much for for spending time with us I
think it was very very interesting
opinionated and fascinating as was to be
expected thanks a lot and we'll put a
lot of links in the show notes
to stop you written and further links on
many of the topics we talked about so
with that thank you again and thanks for
your listeners for listening thank you
very much
[Music]
thanks for listening
SC radio an educational program brought
to you by I Triple E software magazine
for more information about the podcast
including other episodes visit our
website @ SC - radioman to provide
feedback you can write comments on each
episode on the website or write a review
on iTunes mention a message us on
Twitter at se radio or search for the
software engineering radio group on
LinkedIn Google+ or Facebook you can
also email us at team @ SC - radio net
this and all other episodes of SU radio
is licensed under the creative commons
two-point-five license thanks again for
your support
[Music]
[Applause]
you
[Music]